<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>

    <title>@willemsleegers’s website - Dissertation</title>
    <link>https://willemsleegers.github.io/tags/dissertation/</link>
    <description>All entries in Dissertation on website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/dissertation/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      
      <item>
        <title>My LaTeX dissertation template</title>
        <link>https://willemsleegers.github.io/posts/my-latex-dissertation-template/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author> (Willem Sleegers)</author>
        <guid>https://willemsleegers.github.io/posts/my-latex-dissertation-template/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote my PhD dissertation in LaTeX, assuming it would be easier to use (in the long run!) compared to a standard text editor like Pages or Word. Pages does not support all of the functions needed for a beautiful dissertation (step up your game, Apple) and I dislike working in Word. Preferably, I would have written my dissertation in Markdown, but that also seems too limited for a dissertation. Hence, LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether it was worth it. I had to figure out a lot of things, which took me many hours, and the end result was just a whole mixup of packages of which I barely understood what they do. I did not have any experience working in LaTeX so I also took this as an opportunity to figure out whether I like it. My conclusion: I do not. There does not seem to be any kind of vision behind the structure underlying LaTeX, as seen the need for a package for almost every single feature you would like to see in a text document. Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s probably the only workable tool at the moment for a complex document like a dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, then, having a suitable template might do the trick, so I present you with mine. You can find a PDF example of the template &lt;a href=&#34;https://willemsleegers.github.io/../../misc/dissertation_template.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard pages for a dissertation (e.g., supervisor/assessment committee page)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Table of contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two page structure with footers and headers (see example)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bibliography support with in-text references that link to the reference in the References section&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download the LaTeX template &lt;a href=&#34;https://willemsleegers.github.io/../../misc/dissertation_template.zip&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
