<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Willem Sleegers</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Willem Sleegers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My LaTeX dissertation template</title>
      <link>/post/my-latex-dissertation-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/my-latex-dissertation-template/</guid>
      <description>I wrote my PhD dissertation in LaTeX, assuming it would be easier to use (in the long run!) compared to a standard text editor like Pages or Word. Pages does not support all of the functions needed for a beautiful dissertation (step up your game, Apple) and I dislike working in Word. Preferably, I would have written my dissertation in Markdown, but that also seems too limited for a dissertation. Hence, LaTeX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing tidystats</title>
      <link>/post/introducing-tidystats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introducing-tidystats/</guid>
      <description>I am very excited to announce my first ever R package, called tidystats. Its function is to create a single text file containing the output of statistical models. This will enable researchers to store the results of their analyses not just in their manuscripts, but also in an organized file separate from their manuscript that they can freely share with anyone. In this blog post I will go into why I think it is useful to do this and how tidystats works conceptually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a trial-based time variable</title>
      <link>/post/creating-a-trial-based-time-variable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/creating-a-trial-based-time-variable/</guid>
      <description>One of the first issues I ran into when starting to analyze eye tracker data was that the raw data does not contain a trial-based time variable. I expected that the timestamp variable would be a variable that starts at 0 when a trial begins and that it would keep adding up at a rate equal to the sampling frequency, until the end of the trial. Instead, you are likely to get a timestamp variable that looks like a random set of numbers, as shown here:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing multiple data files</title>
      <link>/post/importing-multiple-data-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/importing-multiple-data-files/</guid>
      <description>Combining multiple data files is a regular problem for certain researchers, including myself. In my eye tracker research I collect data for each participant separately. This means that when I want to start preparing my data, I first need to combine the data into one large data frame.
There are many ways to combine separate data files in R. You can read in each file separately and store the result in their own data frame, after which you merge them together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-25-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-25-first-post/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post of my new website, created with the amazing blogdown. Blogdown uses R and Hugo to create a website with blogging functionality. There are various themes to choose from, and this website uses a customized version of the internet-weblog theme. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the code for this website, let me know!
EDIT: I have since changed the theme to the Minimal theme.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>