<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Willem Sleegers</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Willem Sleegers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Colloquium talk: tidystats</title>
      <link>/talk/colloquium_06_03_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/colloquium_06_03_2018/</guid>
      <description>Colloquium talk: tidystats On March 6th, 2018, I gave a colloquium talk at the methodology department of Tilburg University. You can view the slides here:
View slides   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab meeting talk: tidystats</title>
      <link>/talk/labmeeting_26_01_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/labmeeting_26_01_2018/</guid>
      <description>Lab meeting talk: tidystats On January 26th, 2018, I gave a lab meeting presentation on my R package called tidystats. You can see the slides here:
View slides   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing tidystats</title>
      <link>/post/introducing-tidystats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introducing-tidystats/</guid>
      <description>I am very excited to announce my first ever R package, called tidystats. Its function is to create a single text file containing the output of statistical models. This will enable researchers to store the results of their analyses not just in their manuscripts, but also in an organized file separate from their manuscript that they can freely share with anyone. In this blog post I will go into why I think it is useful to do this and how tidystats works conceptually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a trial-based time variable</title>
      <link>/post/creating-a-trial-based-time-variable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/creating-a-trial-based-time-variable/</guid>
      <description>One of the first issues I ran into when starting to analyze eye tracker data was that the raw data does not contain a trial-based time variable. I expected that the timestamp variable would be a variable that starts at 0 when a trial begins and that it would keep adding up at a rate equal to the sampling frequency, until the end of the trial. Instead, you are likely to get a timestamp variable that looks like a random set of numbers, as shown here:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing multiple data files</title>
      <link>/post/importing-multiple-data-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/importing-multiple-data-files/</guid>
      <description>Combining multiple data files is a regular problem for certain researchers, including myself. In my eye tracker research I collect data for each participant separately. This means that when I want to start preparing my data, I first need to combine the data into one large data frame.
There are many ways to combine separate data files in R. You can read in each file separately and store the result in their own data frame, after which you merge them together.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>